The option Greeks course is
designed to familiarize
traders with a set of
risk factors used to monitor
a portfolio's profile,
known as the Greeks.
In this lesson you will learn why
some option prices
are more or less
responsive to changing prices
in the value of the
underlying security.
In this lesson we will
explain the definition of
each of the Greek
variables and explain to
you using an interactive
options calculator
what influences days
to exploration,
interest rates and the
proximity between the
option strike price
and the price of
the underlying have
on the price of an
option over time.
When option traders
understand what
basic inputs determine
the pricing model,
they are ready to move
into dealing with
option portfolio's risk
measures or Greeks.
These risk variables are
called the Greeks because,
with the exception of Vega,
each risk measure is represented
by a letter of the
Greek alphabet.
The Greeks are dependent upon
the inputs for an
options pricing model.
This lesson assumes that
the viewer is familiar with
basic option risks,
strategies and terminology.
As discussed in prior lessons,
options trading provides
additional leverage
to trading equities,
and thus carries increased risk.
Options involve risk and are
not suitable for all investors.
For more information, read
the Characteristics and Risks
of Standardized Options.
For a copy, call 312-542-6901.
An option buyer can loose
the entire premium.
The option seller may have
unlimited risk of loss.
This lesson incorporates an
online options calculator
from the options
Industry Council.
It's a free, interactive
resource available from
optionseducation.org.
Throughout this lesson,
we explain why each
variable impacts the
price of an option,
and we use the calculator to
illustrate those changes.
Access the calculator to
type the inputs on screen
and note the change to call and
put prices as you vary them.
Delta represents the
theoretical change in
an option's price for
a $1 change in the price
of the underlying asset.
For a call option,
Delta will range
from zero to one.
As the price of the
underlying asset increases
beyond the strike price and
gets further in the money,
the Delta will increase
and approach one,
meaning that there is a
greater change to the price of
the option relative to the change
in price of the
underlying assets.
An at-the-money-option,
Germany has
a Delta of approximately 0.5.
Alternatively, Delta
can be thought of as
the probability that an option
will finish in the money.
For a put option,
Delta will range from
negative one to zero.
As the price of the
underlying asset decreases
below the strike price and
gets further in the money,
the Delta will decrease
and approach negative one,
meaning that there
is a greater change
to the price of the option
relative to the change in
the price of the
underlying assets.
An at-the-money-option will
have a Delta of negative 0.5.
Alternatively, the Delta's
absolute value can also be
thought of as the
probability that
an option will land in the money.
As an example, if the
underlying asset price were to
rise from $35.90 to $36.90,
a $1 dollar increase,
the average Delta would
approximate the change
in the option price.
Underlying price, strike
price, interest rate,
volatility and days to
expiration inputs will have
an impact on the Delta.
You can change the
model inputs in
the options calculator and click
calculate to better understand
the impact of the model
inputs on the Delta.
Gamma represents the
rate of change of
Delta for a given change in
the underlying asset's price.
Gamma is largest at
the money and becomes
smaller as options move further
into or out of the money.
The change in an option's
price before expiration
is represented by a curved
line and not a flat line.
The Delta represents the change
at any given point
on the curved line,
and the Gamma describes
the change in
the Delta or curvature
in the line.
For calculus fans, it is the
second order derivative.
Understanding the gamma in
a portfolio is critical for
a trader that is trying to
continuously hedge a portfolio.
As an example, if the
underlying asset price which
arise from $35.90 to $36.91,
a one dollar move,
the old Delta plus
the average Gamma would
approximate the new delta.
Change the model inputs on
the option calculator
and click Calculate
to better understand
the impact of
the model inputs on the Gamma.
Theta describes the relationship
between time and the
price of an option.
Theta only impacts the
extrinsic value of an option,
that's because intrinsic
value does not erode,
it only moves with a change
in the underlying asset price.
As an option nears expiration,
Theta will become
increasingly negative.
The closer an option
is to exploration,
the less time value,
extrinsic value, remains.
Theta measures the
approximate decline in
an options premium due
to the passage of time.
In other words, it measures
that rate at which
an option's extrinsic
value is declining.
Change the options
calculator model inputs
and click Calculate
to better understand
the impact of
the model inputs on the Theta.
Vega represents the change in
the option's price due to
a change in its
implied volatility.
Vega is always greatest at the
money option and decreases
as the underlying
asset price moves
increasingly into the
money or out of the money.
An increase in volatility
of one percent will change
the options price by
approximately the
average of the vega.
Change the model inputs on
the options calculator,
and click Calculate to better
understand the impact of the
model impacts on the vega.
Rho represents
an option's price sensitivity
to interest rates.
The greater the
underlying asset price
and remaining dates
to exploration,
the greater the rho.
As an example, if the
interest rate were to
rise from three and a half
to four and a half percent,
average value of rho would
approximate the change
in the option's price.
Change the model inputs on
the options calculator,
and click Calculate
to better understand
the impact of the model
inputs on the Rho.
Now, let's put it all together.
Using the following assumptions,
we can see the estimated
value of a call option.
Let's use a share
price of a $35.90,
a strike price of $40,
and assume an interest
rate of four percent.
Let's assume an implied
volatility reading of
38.8 percent for the underlying,
and say the option contract
has 38 days to expire.
The call price works out
to be almost 54 cents.
The measure return
for Delta is 0.2214.
This means that for
every one dollar move
in the underlying asset's price,
the option value will change
by approximately 22 cents,
ignoring the impact of Gamma.
Alternatively, there is
a 22 percent chance that
the option will expire at
or above the strike price of $40.
The Gamma reading of
0.0661 tells us that,
should the underlying
price rise by one dollar,
then Delta will rise
by approximately
6.6 cents because of
the curvature in the
options Priceline.
The reading of minus 0.0184
for Theta tells us that
the value of the
option contract drops
approximately 1.8 cents
for each day that passes.
The Vega of 0.0344
tells us that if
implied volatility
were to increase from
38.8 to 39.8 percent,
then the value of the
option would increase
by approximately 3.4 cents.
The reading of 0.0077
for Rho tells us
that if interest rates were
to increase from 4-5 percent,
the option's value would increase
by approximately 0.77 cents.
Now that we have covered
the Greek risk factors,
we encourage you to play with
the free LIC options
calculator to understand how
changes in all of the
inputs are likely to
affect an option's
price and Greeks.
It should be noted that
inputs rarely change
in isolation,
and so it is important to test
the changing multiple
inputs at the same time.